Ruth Gordon Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ruth Gordon Papers 1924-1969 (bulk 1940-1969)
MSS49825
Gordon, Ruth, 1896-1985
6,000 items
26 containers
10.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Actress and playwright. General correspondence, production material, business records, and other papers concerning Gordon's career in movies and the theater.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Ferber, Edna, 1887-1968--Correspondence.; Gordon, Ruth, 1896-1985.; Guinness, Alec, 1914-2000--Correspondence.; Leigh, Vivien, 1913-1967--Correspondence.; Loos, Anita, 1893-1981--Correspondence.; Morse, Robert, 1931- --Correspondence.
Subjects
Drama--Stories, plots, etc.; Motion picture plays, American.; Motion pictures.; Theater.
Occupations
Actresses.; Playwrights.
Provenance
The papers of Ruth Gordon, actress and playwright, were deposited in the Library of Congress by Gordon in 1969 and converted to a gift and purchase in 2008.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the papers of Gordon's husband, Garson Kanin.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Ruth Gordon are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ruth Gordon (1896-1985) span the years 1924-1969, with the bulk of the material concentrated between 1940 and 1969. Included in the collection are correspondence, scripts, financial records, and other material relating mainly to the plays and motion pictures in which Gordon appeared. The papers are organized into four series: General Correspondence; Articles, Drama, and Motion Picture File; Financial Records; and Miscellany.
The General Correspondence consists mainly of letters received by Gordon, with only a scattered number of her replies. The correspondence relates primarily to her career as an actress and author and includes a substantial number of letters of particular interest from Edna Ferber, Alex Guinness, Vivien Leigh, Anita Loos, and Robert Morse.
Included in the Articles, Drama, and Motion Picture File are scripts and screenplays (many in sequential drafts that show the evolution of the work into its final form), financial records, publicity material, and reviews of the works. There is also correspondence relating to specific plays and motion pictures. A group of financial records contain Gordon's bank statements and cancelled checks for the years 1937-1957.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
General Correspondence, 1924-1967
Article, Drama, and Motion Picture File, 1945-1969
Financial Records, 1937-1959
Miscellany
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1924-1967 (Box 1-3)
  Mainly letters received with a few replies.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Abbott, George (Box 1)
  - Adams, Esther (Mrs. Franklin P. Adams) (Box 1)
  - Akins, Zoe (Box 1)
  - Allen, Fred (Box 1)
  - Ames, Winthrop (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Robert W. (Box 1)
  - Ashburn, Carroll (Box 1)
  - Atkinson, Brooks (Box 1)
  - Atkinson, Oriana (Box 1)
  - Ashcroft, Peggy (Box 1)
  - Astor, Minnie (Mrs. Vincent Astor) (Box 1)
  - “A” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, Faith (Box 1)
  - Barillet, Pierre (Box 1)
  - Beaton, Cecil (Box 1)
  - Behrman, Samuel N. (Box 1)
  - Berlin, Irving (Box 1)
  - Bolton, Guy (Box 1)
  - Bouché, René R. (Box 1)
  - Brackett, Charles (Box 1)
  - Braithwaite, Lilian (Box 1)
  - Bromfield, Louis (Box 1)
  - Burke, Billie (Box 1)
  - “B” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Cornell, Polly (Box 1)
  - Cukor, George (Box 1)
  - Curie, Eve (Box 1)
  - “C-D” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Ehrlich, Hedwig (Mrs. Paul Ehrlich) (Box 1)
  - Evans, Maurice (Box 1)
  - “E” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Ferber, Edna (Box 1)
  - Fields, Gracie (Box 1)
  - Ferrer, José (Box 1)
  - Frankfurter, Felix (Box 1)
  - “F” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Gielgud, John (Box 1)
  - Gish, Dorothy (Box 1)
  - Gish, Lillian (Box 1)
  - Golden, John (Box 1)
  - Grant, Cary (Box 1)
  - Guinness, Alec (Box 1)
  - Guinzberg, Harold K. (Box 1)
  - Hardwicke, Helena (Lady Cedric Hardwicke) (Box 1)
  - Harris, Sam H. (Box 1)
  - Harrison, Rex (Box 1)
  - Hart, Mess (Box 1)
  - Helpmann, Robert (Box 1)
  - Hoffmann, Irving (Box 1)
  - Howard, Polly (Mrs. Sidney Howard) (Box 1)
  - Howard, Sidney (Box 1)
  - Howe, James Wong (Box 1)
  - Huston, Walter (Box 1)
  - Hutchins, Robert M. (Box 1)
  - Hyde, John (Box 1)
  - “H” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Isaacs, Stanley M. (Box 1)
  - “I” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Jeans, Ursula (Box 1)
  - Jones, Robert Edmond (Box 1)
  - “J” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Kaufman, George S. (Box 1)
  - Kazan, Elia (Box 1)
  - “K” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Lanchester, Elsa (Box 1)
  - Laughton, Charles (Box 1)
  - Lawford, Ernest (Box 1)
  - Lawrence, Gertrude (Box 1)
  - Leigh, Vivien (Box 1)
  - Lillie, Beatrice (Box 2)
  - Leontovitch, Eugenie (Box 2)
  - Loos, Anita (Box 2)
  - Lindsay, Howard (Box 2)
  - Logan, Joshua (Box 2)
  - Lubitsch, Niccla (Box 2)
  - Luce, Clare Boothe (Box 2)
  - “L” miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - MacArthur, Charles (Box 2)
  - McCarthy, Frank (Box 2)
  - McCowen, Alec (Box 2)
  - McKay, Scott (Box 2)
  - McKenna, Kenneth (Box 2)
  - McQueen, Steve (Box 2)
  - Macrae, Arthur (Box 2)
  - “Mc” miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Martin, Mary (Box 2)
  - Massey, Dorothy (Box 2)
  - Massey, Raymond (Box 2)
  - Merrick, David (Box 2)
  - Morse, May (Box 2)
  - Morse, Richard (Box 2)
  - Morse, Robert (Box 2)
  - Murphy, Noel (Box 2)
  - “M” miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Niven, David (Box 2)
  - “H-O” miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Pardoll, David (Box 2)
  - Patterson, Joseph Medill (Box 2)
  - Peck, Gregory (Box 2)
  - Pitts, Zazu (Box 2)
  - Porter, Cole (Box 2)
  - Porterfield, Robert (Box 2)
  - “P-Q” miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Redgrave, Michael (Box 2)
  - Reiner, Carlotta (Mrs. Fritz Reiner) (Box 2)
  - Ritter, Thelma (Box 2)
  - Rogers, Ginger (Box 2)
  - Ross, Ariane (Mrs. Harold W. Ross) (Box 2)
  - Ross, Emily (Box 2)
  - Rosten, Norman (Box 2)
  - “R” miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Sell, Henry B. (Box 2)
  - Selznick, David O. See also Container 1, Hyde, John (Box 2)
  - Shean, Al (Box 2)
  - Sherwood, Madeline (Box 2)
  - Sherwood, Robert E. (Box 2)
  - Shubert, Lee (Box 2)
  - Simonson, Lee (Box 2)
  - Skinner, Cornelia Otis (Box 2)
  - Snow, Carmel (Box 2)
  - Sothern, Ann (Box 2)
  - Soulé, Henri (Box 2)
  - Sterling, Jan (Box 2)
  - Stickney, Dorothy (Box 2)
  - Sullivan, Ed (Box 2)
  - Sweet, Blanche (Box 2)
  - Swope, Herbert Bayard (Box 2)
  - “S” miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Tillstrom, Burr (Box 3)
  - “T-U” miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Valentine (Valentina Nicholaevna Sanina Schlee) (Box 3)
  - Van Druten, John (Box 3)
  - Verdon, Gwen (Box 3)
  - Vidor, Doris (Mrs. Charles Vidor) (Box 3)
  - “V” miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Warner, Jack (Box 3)
  - Webster, Margaret (Box 3)
  - Welles, Orson (Box 3)
  - Wescott, Glenway (Box 3)
  - West, Rebecca (Box 3)
  - White, Blwyn Brooks (Box 3)
  - Whitty, May (Box 3)
  - Williams, Emlyn (Box 3)
  - Winter, Ella (Box 3)
  - Wodehouse, Pelham Grenville (Box 3)
  - Welfert, Ira (Box 3)
  - Woods, Marion K. (Box 3)
  - Woollcott, Alexander (Box 3)
  - “W” miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Unidentified (Box 3)
- Article, Drama, and Motion Picture File, 1945-1969 (Box 4-14)
  Articles, outlines, scripts, correspondence and other production material.
  Organized by type of work and therein alphabetically by title or type of material.
  - Article, “How to Think Up a Play” (Box 4)
  - Dramas (Box 4)
    - The Loves of Cass McGuire (Box 4)
      - Script (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
        - Anspach, Andrew A. (Box 4)
        - Brown, Slade (Box 4)
        - Cornell, Katherine (Box 4)
        - Ehrlich, Richard A. (Box 4)
        - Friel, Brian (Box 4)
        - Gershe, Leonard (Box 4)
        - Goetz, William (Box 4)
        - Lefkowitz, Nathan (Box 4)
        - Lerman, Leo (Box 4)
        - Lieberson, Coddard (Box 4)
        - Lyons, Leonard (Box 4)
        - McDowall, Roddy (Box 4)
        - Merrick, David (Box 4)
        - Nichols, Mike (Box 4)
        - Sinatra, Frank (Box 4)
        - Turgeon, Peter (Box 4)
    - The Matchmaker (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
        - Colbert, Claudette (Box 4)
        - Cukor, George (Box 4)
        - Cutts, Patricia (Box 4)
        - Goetz, William (Box 4)
        - Guthrie, Tyrone (Box 4)
        - Henderson, Ray (Box 4)
        - Laughton, Charles (Box 4)
        - Marx, Harpo (Box 4)
        - Tracy, Spencer (Box 4)
        - Webb, Clifton (Box 4)
      - Box office statements, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Production (Box 4)
      - Programs (Box 5)
      - Publicity (Box 5)
      - Reviews, (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - Salary vouchers (Box 5)
      - Miscellany (Box 5)
    - A Very Rich Woman, scripts, (5 folders); (8 folders) (Box 5, Box 6)
    - Years Ago (Box 6)
      - Script, (2 folders); (8 folders) (Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
      - Correspondence (Box 8)
        - Gordon, Max (Box 8)
        - Lazar, Irving (Box 8)
        - Massey, Dorothy (Box 8)
        - Porterfield, Robert (Box 8)
        - “A-W” miscellaneous (Box 8)
      - Music and set design (Box 8)
      - Royalty earnings (Box 8)
      - Printed matter (Box 8)
  - Motion pictures (Box 9)
    - The Actress (Box 9)
      - Outline (Box 9)
      - Screenplay, (9 folders); (8 folders); (1 folder) (Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13)
      - Correspondence (Box 13)
        - Cukor, George (Box 13)
        - “G-S” miscellaneous (Box 13)
      - Miscellany (Box 13)
    - Lord Love a Duck, screenplay (Box 13)
    - Rosemary's Baby (Box 13)
      - Screenplay, (2 folders) (Box 13)
      - Publicity (Box 13)
      - Shooting schedule and production call sheets (Box 13)
      - Printed matter, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - What Ever Happened to Aunt Alice? (Box 14)
      - Screenplay, (4 folders) (Box 14)
      - Shooting schedule and production call sheets (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous papers (Box 14)
      - Printed matter (Box 14)
- Financial Records, 1937-1959 (Box 15-25)
  Bank statements and cancelled checks.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1937-1938 (Box 15)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 16)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 17)
  - 1943-1944 (Box 18)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 19)
  - 1947 (Box 20)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 21)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 22)
  - 1952-1954 (Box 23)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 24)
  - 1957, 1959 (Box 25)
- Miscellany (Box 26)
  Printed biographical material and a miscellaneous item.
  Unarragned
  - Clippings and miscellaneous printed matter, (2 folders) (Box 26)